<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="akarasulu@apache.org">Alex Karasulu</author>
    <title>Apache Directory Project: PMC Voting</title>
  </properties> 


    <body> 
        <section name="Voting Procedures">
            
            <p>This document details how the Directory PMC has agreed to handle 
              voting.</p>
            
            <subsection name="People Involved in the Voting Process">
                
                <subsection name="The Proposer">
                    
                    <p>
                     The proposer is the one who comes up with the
                        discussion that needs to be addressed.  Any
                        member of the Directory community may start the
                        discussion. The proposer must follow the
                        procedures listed under the heading "Prior to
                        the Vote".</p>
                    
                </subsection>
                
                <subsection name="The Vote Administrator">
                    
                    <p>The vote administrator is the person who
                        tallies the votes and reports the results.
                        The person who actually puts a proposal up for
                        vote is usually the vote administrator,
                        although this task can be taken on by someone
                        else.</p>
                    
                </subsection>
                
                <subsection name="The Voter">
                    
                    <p>A voter is someone who expresses support,
                        opposition or abstention for the subject being
                        voted on.  A voter must be a Directory PMC
                        member. Input is appreciated from committers
                        and all other members of the community, but
                        only votes from PMC members are counted.</p>
                    
                </subsection>
            </subsection>
            
            <subsection name="Prior to the Vote">
                
                <p>Before any vote can take place, the subject must be
                    discussed. All such discussions take place on the
                    Directory developer or PMC mailing list, and have the
                    text "[PROPOSAL]" in the subject line.  That
                    practice alerts members to the fact that you
                    eventually intend to call a vote on the
                    subject.</p>
                
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="The Vote">
                
                <p>When the proposal is ready to be adopted by the
                    community, the Proposer will call for a vote on
                    the Directory developers or PMC mailing list. The
                    call for vote must have the text "[PMC:VOTE]" in
                    the subject line.  That practice alerts the
                    members to the fact that the prior proposal is now
                    ready to vote on, and discussion should stop for
                    the proposal.</p>
                
                <subsection name="How to Vote">
                    
                    <p>The voter responds to the call for vote with an
                        expression of support, opposition, or
                        abstention.  The exact way to express the
                        voter's position is listed below:</p>
                    
                    <ul>
                        <li>+1  a vote supporting the subject</li>
                        <li>+0  a vote abstaining from the subject (but showing some support).</li>
                        <li> 0  a vote abstaining from the subject.</li>
                        <li>-0  a vote abstaining from the subject (but showing disapproval).</li>
                        <li>-1  a vote opposing the subject</li>
                    </ul>
                </subsection>
                
                <subsection name="Counting Votes">
                    
                    <p>The vote administrator will count only the last
                        vote from each voter.  That means a voter may
                        change their vote at any time during the
                        duration of the vote. All votes (+1, -1, +0,
                        -0 and 0) count toward quorum, but +0, -0 and
                        0 do not count when determining majority.</p>
                        </subsection>
                
                <subsection name="Types of Votes">
                    
                    <p>There are two classes of votes: a Qualified
                        Majority Vote and a Normal Majority Vote. In
                        both types of votes, only +1 and -1 votes
                        count toward majority.</p>
                    
                    <subsection name="Qualified Majority Vote">
                        
                        <p>Any vote that affects the texts "Directory PMC
                            Charter" or "Directory PMC Policies and
                            Procedures" is a Qualified Majority
                            Vote. For this type of vote to pass, it
                            requires that there are more than twice as
                            many +1 votes as -1 votes.</p> </subsection>
                    
                    <subsection name="Normal Majority Vote">
                        
                        <p>All votes that do not fall under the
                            heading of Qualified Majority Vote are
                            handled as a Normal Majority Vote. If
                            there are more +1 votes than -1 votes,
                            then the vote has passed.</p> </subsection>
                            </subsection>
                
                <subsection name="Voting Qualifications">
                    
                    <p>In order for any vote to be considered binding
                        it must have quorum, and be held for the
                        proper amount of time.</p>
                    
                </subsection>
                
                <subsection name="Quorum">
                    
                    <p>For all votes, there must be at least three (3)
                        voters and half (1/2) of the PMC must cast a
                        vote. When determining quorum, all votes (+1,
                        -1, +0, -0 and 0) count.</p> </subsection>
                
                <subsection name="Duration">
                    
                    <p>All votes will be open for an initial period of
                        one week.  The Vote Administrator may close
                        the vote at any time after that period if
                        quorum has been achieved.  If quorum could not
                        be reached within the initial one-week period,
                        the vote will remain open for one additional
                        week.  If the vote still has not achieved
                        quorum, then it is considered failed.  The
                        proposer can choose to bring it up later when
                        quorum can be reached.</p> </subsection>
                        </subsection>
            
            <subsection name="After the Vote">
                
                <p>When the vote is closed, the results of the vote
                    are summarized by the Vote Administrator.  The
                    vote administrator will send an email to the
                    Directory developers or PMC list with the text
                    "[PMC:VOTE-RESULT]" in the subject that has the
                    summary.  The summary will include the count of
                    all +1, +0, 0, -0, and -1 responses, and the final
                    verdict of whether the subject passed.</p>
                    </subsection>
            
            <subsection name="Disagreements">
                
                <p>Disagreements concerning voting may be directed to
                    the Chair. The Chair's opinion shall be final and
                    binding upon the PMC.</p>
                
            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
