<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="akarasulu@apache.org">Alex Karasulu</author>
    <title>Welcome !</title>
    <description>The Apache Directory Project aims to produce a high performance and production quality LDAP server written in Java.</description>
  </properties>
  <body>
    
    <section name="What is it?">
      <p>
        Before going into all the details here's what the Apache Directory
        Server looks like from an architectural perspective.
      </p>

      <map name="directory">
  <area shape="rect" alt="Network Layer" href="subprojects/network/index.html" target="subprojects/network/index.html" title="Network Layer" coords="39,155,603,175" />
  <area shape="rect" alt="Protocol Providers" href="subprojects/apacheds/subsubprojects/index.html" target="subprojects/apacheds/subsubprojects/index.html" title="Protocol Providers" coords="44,175,595,207" />
  <area shape="rect" alt="Apache Directory Server Core" href="subprojects/apacheds/subsubprojects/index.html" target="subprojects/apacheds/subsubprojects/index.html" title="Apache Directory Server Core" coords="209,277,612,443" />
  <area shape="rect" alt="Kerberos Provider" href="subprojects/apacheds/subsubprojects/index.html" target="subprojects/apacheds/subsubprojects/index.html" title="Kerberos Provider" coords="457,210,530,225" />
  <area shape="rect" alt="LDAP Provider" href="subprojects/apacheds/subsubprojects/index.html" target="subprojects/apacheds/subsubprojects/index.html" title="LDAP Provider" coords="374,210,448,225"/>
  <area shape="rect" alt="DNS Provider" href="subprojects/apacheds/subsubprojects/index.html" target="subprojects/apacheds/subsubprojects/index.html" title="DNS Provider" coords="209,210,283,224" />
  <area shape="rect" alt="DHCP Provider" href="subprojects/apacheds/subsubprojects/index.html" target="subprojects/apacheds/subsubprojects/index.html" title="DHCP Provider" coords="128,210,202,225" />
  <area shape="rect" alt="NTP Provider" href="subprojects/apacheds/subsubprojects/index.html" target="subprojects/apacheds/subsubprojects/index.html" title="NTP Provider" coords="44,209,118,224" />
</map>
<img usemap="directory" src="images/50k-ft-architecture.png"/>
    </section>
    <section name="Our Vision">
      <p>
        Our primary vision (others also outlined below) is to build an 
        enterprise directory server platform (and its components) where 
        other Internet services snap in to store their data within the 
        directory so they may be managed using LDAP.  From the image 
        above you'll see the architecture is designed so services besides
        LDAP like DNS, DHCP, SLP and Kerberos will snap in.  Other services
        like UDDI can also be implemented and snapped in.  These services 
        will use a common networking layer and each can be toggled on and
        off according to the needs of the environment.  apseda, mina, or 
        sedang are various frameworks used for the common network layer. 
        These services share the common network layer and back their data 
        within the Apache Directory Server's backing stores without any 
        network latency or going through the LDAP line protocol.  NTP btw
        is the only exception and it's there to remedy the need for time 
        sync for replication and other time sensitive protocols like kerberos.
        Its implementation here is intended to prevent any dependency on
        external infrastructure.
      </p>

      <p>
        Other aspects to our vision include becoming the JNDI goto project and 
        also becoming the one stop shop for all directory and naming concerns 
        here at the ASF.  These concerns may be outside of the scope of JNDI 
        or may not even fall under Java.
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
