<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
      <author email="akarasulu@apache.org">Alex Karasulu</author>
      <author email="erodriguez@apache.org">Enrique Rodriguez</author>
    <title>Protocol Provider Subprojects</title>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="Protocol Providers">
      <p> The Apache Directory Project's Protocol Providers are Java implementations of
        standard Internet services. These Protocol Providers, in conjunction with the MINA
        network layer and the Apache Directory read-optimized backing store, provide
        easy-to-use yet fully-featured Internet services. As implemented within the Apache
        Directory, these services benefit from: </p>
      <ul>
        <li>Standard directory model and schema support</li>
        <li>Standard LDAP data interchange format (LDIF) (RFC 2849)</li>
        <li>Optional LDAP management</li>
        <li>UDP and TCP Support (MINA)</li>
        <li>Traffic throttling (MINA)</li>
        <li>Overload shielding (MINA)</li>
        <li>Easy POJO embeddability for containers such as Geronimo, JBoss, and OSGi</li>
      </ul>
      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>Name</th>
          <th>Description</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <a href="providers/ldap/index.html">Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP)
              Provider</a>
          </td>
          <td>
            <p> An LDAP implementation based on <a
              href="http://www.faqs.org/rfcs/rfc2251.html">RFC 2251</a>. Apache LDAP
              provides lightweight access to the Apache Directory backing store.</p>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <a href="providers/kerberos/index.html">Kerberos Protocol Provider</a>
          </td>
          <td>
            <p> A Kerberos implementation based on <a
              href="http://www.faqs.org/rfcs/rfc1510.html">RFC 1510</a>. Apache
              Kerberos verifies the identities of principals (users or services) on
              an unprotected network using principal information stored in the Apache
              Directory backing store.</p>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <a href="providers/changepw/index.html">Change Password Protocol Provider</a>
          </td>
          <td>
            <p> A Change Password implementation based on <a
              href="http://www.faqs.org/rfcs/rfc3244.html">RFC 3244</a>. Apache
              Change Password uses Kerberos infrastructure to allow users to securely
              set initial passwords or to change existing passwords stored in the
              Apache Directory backing store.</p>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <a href="providers/dns/index.html">Domain Name System (DNS) Protocol Provider</a>
          </td>
          <td>
            <p> A DNS implementation based on <a
              href="http://www.faqs.org/rfcs/rfc1034.html">RFC 1034</a>. Apache DNS
              serves host name to address mappings and other resource record types
              using resource records stored in the Apache Directory backing store.</p>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <a href="providers/ntp/index.html">Network Time Protocol (NTP) Provider</a>
          </td>
          <td>
            <p> An NTP implementation based on <a
              href="http://www.faqs.org/rfcs/rfc2030.html">RFC 2030</a>. Apache NTP
              supports time synchronization for LDAP replication and the Kerberos
              protocol, eliminating the need for external infrastructure.</p>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <a href="providers/dhcp/index.html">Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP)
              Provider</a>
          </td>
          <td>
            <p> A DHCP implementation based on <a
              href="http://www.faqs.org/rfcs/rfc2131.html">RFC 2131</a>. Apache DHCP
              helps configure hosts using configuration information stored in the
              Apache Directory backing store.</p>
          </td>
        </tr>
      </table>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
