<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document> 
  <properties>
    <author email="erodriguez@apache.org">Enrique Rodriguez</author>
    <title>Apache Directory Project: Contributors</title>
  </properties>
  <body> 
    <section name="Enrique Rodriguez">
      <p>
        (erodriguez at apache dot org)          
      </p>
      <p> 
        Enrique is founder and lead developer for the Apache Kerberos server.
      </p>
      <p>
        Enrique lives north of Boston in Burlington, MA, on the Route 128 tech corridor.  Burlington
        is the east coast home for Oracle, Sun, Cognos, Siemens, and many others.
      </p>
      <p>
        Enrique was formerly a systems architect contracting for Microsoft Consulting Services, the director of
        implementation and principal product architect for a dot-com, and the Director of Global Systems for
        Liberty Mutual Insurance.  His recreation and work experiences have taken him to 47 U.S. states
        and to over 100 other locations across six continents.
      </p>
      <p>
        Enrique earned a degree in Electrical Engineering and minored in the Biology of Behavior at Rensselaer (RPI).
        Enrique is an avid mountaineer and has climbed the highest mountains in North America (Mt. McKinley, United
        States), South America (Aconcagua, Argentina), Europe (Elbrus, Russian Federation), and Africa (Kilimanjaro,
        Tanzania). Between climbing expeditions, Enrique competes for Team Mercury Multisport in triathlons and marathons.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section name="Background">
      <p> 
        Enrique was dreaming of an all-Java stack and found there was a hole where Kerberos should have been.  After 3
        long days, he had authentication working.  Within a couple of weeks he was able to migrate his home network off
        of MIT Kerberos.  Realizing there would be tremendous potential if Kerberos were integrated tightly into the
        Apache Directory, he approached Alex Karasulu in the late summer of 2004.  Soon thereafter, the Kerberos
        codebase was granted to the Apache Software Foundation and Alex began to transform the standalone Kerberos
        server into a plugin protocol provider that heavily leveraged the SEDA frontend framework and tightly integrated
        with the Eve read-optimized backing store.
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>

