<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document> 
  <properties>
    <author email="trustin@apache.org">Trustin Lee</author>
    <title>Apache Directory Project: Contributors</title>
  </properties>
  <body> 
    <section name="Trustin Lee">
      <p>
        (trustin at apache dot org)          
      </p>

      <p> 
        Trustin is a lead developer for the Apache SEDA framework, and he is
        working on MINA (Multipurpose Infrastructure for Network Applications)
        to improve SEDA framework from ground-up.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        Trustin was born in 1980.  He started programming with built-in BASIC
        interpreter in MSX mini computer when he was 8 years old.  He enjoyed
        game programming and problem solving using assembly language, C, and
        C++.  Finally, he wins bronze medal at Korea information olympiad in
        1998.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        He worked for several companies as a part time worker who
        writes high-performance network server applications and a few web
        applications after he started to major computer science in Yonsei
        university in South Korea.  After graduation, he is working for Arreo
        Communications, Inc which is one of the biggest SMS (mobile short
        message service) provider in Korea.
      </p>

      <p>
        Trustin spends his free time taking photos with his lovely SLR camera
        and listening to his favorite compact discs (Japanese pop and Jazz).
      </p>
    </section>
    <section name="Background">
      <p>
        Trustin was getting bored implementing tedious legacy protocols.  He
        thought he could save himself by creating a generic framework for
        network applications.  The name of the framework was 'Netty' and
        it has been improved for a couple of years until java.nio package is
        introduced.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        NIO changed lots of things, and it impacted Netty.  New version of
        Netty was named to Netty2 and released as open source.  It gave Trustin
        the experience of open source community and made him fascinated by it.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        Enrique Rodriguez was one of the users of Netty2, and he brought great 
        fortune to Trustin.  He metioned Netty2 when he approached Alex
        Karasulu, who was the lead for the Apache Directory project.  Alex was
        developing SEDA framework as a network application framework at that
        time.  He proposed Trustin to get the power of both together and make
        the best network application framework available, and the work is in
        progress actively.
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>

