<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="akarasulu@apache.org">Alex Karasulu</author>
    <title>ASN.1 and BER Information</title>
  </properties>
  <body>

    <section name="ASN.1 and BER Information">
      <subsection name="Background">
        <p>
          The BER encoding for ASN.1 was defined within ITU specification
          X.690 along with the Canonical and Distinguished Encoding Rules.
          A copy of this document along with other useful documents and books
          on ASN.1 and its encodings can be obtained for free here:
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
        <table>
        <tr><th>Document</th><th>Description</th></tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <a href="http://lesbeshy.notlong.com">X.690 (07/02)</a>
          </td>
          <td>
            Information technology - ASN.1 encoding rules: Specification of
            Basic Encoding Rules (BER), Canonical Encoding Rules (CER) and
            Distinguished Encoding Rules (DER)
          </td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>
            <a href="http://offburie.notlong.com">X.680 (07/02)</a>
          </td>
          <td>
            Information technology - Abstract Syntax Notation One (ASN.1):
            Specification of basic notation
          </td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>
            <a href="http://www.oss.com/asn1/bookreg.html">ASN.1 Complete</a>
          </td>
          <td>
            A verbose yet truely complete book on ASN.1 and various encoding
            mechanisms.  Easy to read since the author takes almost a
            conversational tone.
          </td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td>
            <a href="http://www.oss.com/asn1/bookreg2.html">
              ASN.1 - Communication between heterogeneous systems</a>
          </td>
          <td>
            Also a very complete book on ASN.1 and various encoding mechanisms.
            A little more difficult to read but seems to be much better
            organized and more exacting.  I use both books in conjunction
            often switching between the two based on my mood :-).  Both are
            most excellent - thanks to both authors for graciously providing
            their books online.
          </td>
        </tr>
        </table>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="BER Tag, Value, Length Tuples">
        <p>
          BER stands for Basic Encoding Rules.  These rules describe how to
          encode and decode basic data types and composite data structures
          to and from TLV streams.  A TLV hence may be primitive (atomic) or
          constructed (nested) where the value component contains other TLVs.
          The T is for the Tag a numeric type identifier, the L is for the
          length of the data carried in the third V component, the value.
          Outside of this very trivial introduction there is very little to
          the encoding.  Readers should look at the relatively short
          specification for referrence regarding the exact encoding for
          various data types using TLV tuples.  The books above also have
          appendices for the various encodings which are longer than the
          actual specification yet more explanitory.
        </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>