<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document> 
  <properties>
    <author email="wesmckean@apache.org">Wes McKean</author>
    <title>Apache Directory Project: Contributors</title>
  </properties>
  <body> 
    <section name="Wes McKean">
      <p>(wesmckean at apache dot org)</p>
      <p>
      Wes is one of the newest members of the LDAPd group, and a founding
      member of the Apache Directory Project, having joined the Apache Software
      Foundation when LDAPd was absorbed into the Apache incubator.
      </p>
    </section>
    
    <section name="Background">
      <p>
	      As an IT profressional, entrepreneur, and father, Wes has worked in the Atlanta
	      metro area for over 14 years.  Wes has always had a special love for Open Source
	      initiatives and their authors, having used open source applications with many of
	      the companies for which he has worked.  Wes discovered LDAPd and Alex Karasulu
	      while searching for an open source project to integrate into his current employer's
	      commercial offerings.  Having found LDAPd on SourceForge, he immediately got
	      excited about the synergies between the two products, and realized that Wes and
	      LDAPd had a lot to offer each other.
      </p>
      
      <p>  
          Wes is current involved with the Snickers subproject.  Snickers is a drop in
          replacement for the ASN.1 codec used by Eve.  
          The Snickers subproject itself is broken up
          into compiler and coder/decoder subprojects.  Snickers will be a <b>non-blocking,
          event driven</b> parser, setting itself apart from currently available open
          source and commercial offerings.
      </p>
      
      <p> 
          Wes has taken a great interest in the database sub-system used by Eve and the orignal
          LDAPd server.  He has written several new backends, and also a entirely new indexing
          scheme to handle the various technical challenges of the LDAP persistent storage.
      </p>
    </section>
    
  </body>
</document>

