<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="akarasulu@apache.org">Alex Karasulu</author>
    <title>Apache Directory Project: PMC</title>
  </properties> 

  <body>
    <section name="">
      <p>
        For now because we are within the incubator we do not have a PMC but 
        the incubator's equivalent of one for a incubated project.  Until we
        exit the incubator the this PPMC will operate using the PMC guidelines
        below.
      </p>
    </section>
    
	  <section name="Informative material only">
	    <p>These pages exist only to provide some down-to-earth insight
	    in how things work at the ASF. They're informative only, not
	    normative. They may contain errors or inadequacies. IANAL.</p>
	  </section>
          <section name="So what is this PMC thing?">
            <p>Apache is a legal entity, i.e. a real non-profit organisation,
	    with a charter, members, a board, a president, etc. You can
	    read all about that
	    <a href="http://www.apache.org/foundation/">here</a></p>
	    
	    <p>A PMC, Project Management Committee, is a group of people
	    appointed with the task of managing something that fits with the
	    Apache Software Foundation goals. The Directory PMC, for example,
	    is tasked with managing the Apache Directory Project.</p>
	  </section>
	  <section name="What, management?! We've already got plenty of those at work!">
	    <p>We're all programmers, and that is what we want to occupy us
	    with. We like to share and work on our software together, which
	    is why we make it free software. However, there is always some
	    stuff which still requires management.</p>
	    
	    <p>For example, in order to protect ourselves and our users, all
	    software hosted at Apache must be properly copyrighted to the ASF,
	    and licensed under the ASF license. This is something the PMC is
	    responsible for.</p>
	    
	    <p>Also, remember that the PMC consists of the same people that do
	    the development work. There's no "bossing around" here. The PMC
	    exists only to facilitate free software developers in "doing their
	    thing", just like the ASF exists "to provide organizational, legal,
	    and financial support for the Apache Open Source software
	    projects".</p>
	  </section>
	  <section name="The PMC Chair and Officer of the Foundation">
	    <p>The position of Directory PMC chair is an important one; the PMC
	    chair has special responsibilities and privileges as detailed in
	    the ASF bylaws.</p>
	  </section>
        <section name="Project Management Committee">
        <p>For now all members form the current Directory PPMC:</p>
      </section>
    </body> 
</document>
