<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="akarasulu@apache.org">Alex Karasulu</author>
    <title>Subversion</title>
  </properties> 
  <body>

    <section name="About Subversion">
      <p> Subversion is an open source version control system, released under 
        an Apache/BSD-style license. This application was designed, and is on 
        track to replace CVS. Users familiar with CVS will be able to jump into 
        Subversion easily as most of the interface is the same. Details about 
        the benefits and technical information can be viewed on the Subversion 
        <a href="http://subversion.tigris.org/">home page</a>, here are just a 
        few of the highlights: 
        <ul> 
          <li> Atomic Commits </li> 
          <li> Versioned meta-data </li> 
          <li> Revision numbers are per-commit, not per-file</li> 
          <li> Uses Apache web server and WebDAV/DeltaV for network communication </li> 
          <li> Enables binary diffs </li> 
        </ul> 
      </p>
    </section> 
    
    <section name="Getting Help">     
      <p> The subversion book is an excellent resource for users and 
        administrators, it can obtained <a href= 
        "http://svnbook.red-bean.com/html-chunk/">here</a>.
      </p>
    </section>
    
    <section name="Browsing the Repository">
      <p>
        You can browse the repository using ViewSVN <a href=
       "http://svn.apache.org/viewcvs.cgi/directory/?root=Apache-SVN">
        here</a>.
      </p>
    </section>
    
    <section name="Getting the sources from Subversion">
      <p>
        There's a few options for you.  Subversion can be run from
        the command line (Linux or Windows) and there are also an 
        increasing number of GUI's and plugin's.      
      </p>
  
      <subsection name="Command-line tools">
        <p>
          The SVN utilities are available as native Windows, Linux, and solaris 
          binaries. The source is also avaiable for other operating systems.  
          The binaries and source can be obatined from the Subversion <a href="http://subversion.tigris.org/project_packages.html"> download 
          page.</a>. 
        </p>
        
        <p>To get the entire project, run the following command</p>
        <source>
          svn co https://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/directory
        </source>
      
        <p>
          This will take a while, depending on your connection. Go ahead and 
          grab yourself a coffee or ten.  When done, you should have checked 
          out all Directory sources. You will now need to install <a href=
          "http://maven.apache.org/">Apache Maven</a>, our default build tool if 
          you haven't already. 
        </p>
      </subsection>
  
      <subsection name="Use TortoiseSVN">
        <p>
          <a href="http://tortoisesvn.tigris.org/">TortoiseSVN</a> is a neat 
          extension for the Windows Explorer which integrates SVN. Using it is 
          real simple:
        </p>
  
        <p>
          After you've created a folder where you want to check out the sources 
          to, right-click and select SVN Checkout.  Then, fill out the settings 
          like in the screenshot below, and then click ok.<br/>
          <img src="images/tortoisesvn-setting.jpg" alt="screenshot of SVN settings"/>
        </p>
      </subsection>    
    </section>
    
    <section name="Commit with Subversion">   
      <subsection name="Getting Access to Subversion">
        <p>
          Before you can commit to the subversion repository, you will
          need to create an SVN password.  To do this, log on to 
          minotaur.apache.org and run the following command:
        </p>
        <source>
          svnpasswd 
        </source>
        <p>
          The will ask you for a subversion password.  This is the user 
          and password you will use when checking in code.  
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Commit Code Via Command Line">
        <p>
          When you commit code to subversion, it will try to use the
          username you are logged in as on the current system. If this 
          is different than your subversion username, you will need to
          specifiy this on the commit statement.  Subversion will prompt 
          for your password when you run the command.  Note the is the 
          SVN password, which is not the same as your minotaur password
          This password can be entered as a command line argument to 
          avoid interaction.  The follow command line will commit with a 
          specified username and password:
        </p>
        <source>
          svn commit --username <i>username</i> --password <i>password</i>
        </source>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Commit with Tortoise">
        <p>
          To commit with TortoiseSVN, simply right click on the directory
          you want to run the commit from and select commit.  A list of
          files changed will be displayed with a text box for a log message.
          At this point you can select which files should be committed and
          enter you log text.  Select OK to start the commit, a dialog box
          will appear prompting for username and password.  You will also
          be able to select a check box to remember the credentials.  If you
          select this check box, you will not be prompted for information in
          the future
        </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
