<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document> 
  <properties>
    <author email="akarasulu@apache.org">Alex Karasulu</author>
    <title>Apache Directory Project: Contributors</title>
  </properties>
  <body> 

    <section name="Alex Karasulu">
      <p>(akarasulu at apache dot org)</p>
      
      <p>
        Alex wrote the LDAPd pure Java LDAP server and founded the LDAPd Group.
        He eventually disolved the LDAPd Group and proposed and founded the 
        Directory Project at Apache which absorbed the code base to the LDAPd 
        Directory Server.
      </p>
      
      <subsection name="Some Background">
        <p> 
          As a want-to-be enterprise architect and developer Alex had searched for a way 
          to consolidate common data within an infrastructure into one single 
          location to centralize it's management and allow for shared access.  
          Such a centralized database would make enterprise integration of 
          several applications and processes depending on this common 
          information that much easier without duplication and consistancy 
          issues.
        </p>
        
        <p>
          Alex first experimented with a centralized database to initially store
          user accounts, passwords and authorization profiles for various
          applications and resources within an enterprise.   Unfortunatly the 
          use of an RDBMS was inhibiting.  It was a single point of failure 
          which wound up becoming a bottle neck.  Furthermore the RDBMS was
          not very conducive toward managing heirarchical data and delegating
          control over it.  A new storage and access paradigm was required and
          that's when Alex encountered the directory.
        </p>
        
        <p>
          After studying up on X.500 and LDAP Alex decided to design corporate
          directories to facilitate in enterprise application integration and
          the realization of workflows across these systems.  His experience 
          lead to encounters with various directory servers which disappointed
          him.  The directory servers encountered were a decade away from being
          as robust as the RDBMS is for application developement.  Some of the 
          rich features in the RDBMS have yet to be introduced into the world 
          of the directory server or require a massive workaround to implement.
          Things like stored procedures and triggers were most high on that 
          list.
        </p>
        
        <p>
          Finally on October 16th 2002 Alex decided to write his own LDAP server
          which had support for triggers and stored procedures.  On this day he 
          registered a Sourceforge project called LDAPd and began building an
          LDAP server.  He also founded the LDAPd Group which worked on the 
          LDAPd server.  Eventually Jeff Machols, Robb Penoyer, Wes McKean and 
          others joined the project.  Before a year the server had 3 releases at
          sourceforge and an invitation was made by Apache to have the 
          LDAPd project move there.   A proposal was written and submitted 
          for the Apache Directory Project on September 3rd 2003.  The proposal 
          was accepted by the ASF into the Apache incubator on October 30th 
          2003.
        </p>
        
        <p>
          The dream of a robust pure Java LDAP server will be realized before 
          exiting the incubator.  Most importantly the server will be free and 
          supported by a healthy community of developers here at the ASF.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name="Alex's Stuff">
        <table>
          <tr><td>Stuff</td><td>Description</td></tr>
          
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="http://sf.net/projects/ldapd">LDAPd</a>
            </td>
            <td>
              This is the old LDAPd Sourceforge project started before the 
              Directory Project existed at the ASF.
            </td>
          </tr>
          
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="../../project-proposal.html">Proposal</a>
            </td>
            <td>
              This is the proposal submitted to the ASF to start the 
              Directory Project as an incubator project.
            </td>
          </tr>
          
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="http://www.jroller.com/page/akarasulu">Blog</a>
            </td>
            <td>
              Weblog containing random events, ideas and discussions.
            </td>
          </tr>
          
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="http://www.apache.org/~akarasulu">Homepage</a>
            </td>
            <td>
              Homepage where you can find resources on directory
              technologies and other peices of information.
            </td>
          </tr>
          
        </table>
      </subsection>
      
    </section>
  </body>
</document>

